Good morning. Today's דף daf is ס"ו. Samech Vav. And as we've
seen yesterday, we're getting into a slightly different theme of discussion. So,
that a little bit continues today, on the one hand, the continuation
of the סוגיא sugya of what things are considered carrying biblically, what's
a rabbinic issue of a concern you'll take it off. But also,
as we'll see, the גמרא Gemara will turn to other matters. So
we start with some משנה. Mishnah. לא תצא האשה במחט הנקובה. Lo
teitzei ha'isha bemachat hanequvah. So until now we've been mentioning focusing on
the woman. Let's remember that by the way, גבי אשה gabeisha what
can a woman wear? And this משנה Mishnah says and the first
משנה Mishnah says the things that it did say לא יצא האיש
בסנדל, lo yeitzei ha'ish besandal, it switched back to a man. So
the first two sets of משניות mishnayot were what can a woman
not wear and a man not wear but if you take it
out it is not a biblical violation, it is only a rabbinic
concern that you'll maybe take it off and show it, or with
this nailed sandal a special issue. And now we talk about issues
that are actually a biblical concern that you might come, that is
actually not considered clothing. So, לא תצא האשה במחט הנקובה. Lo teitzei
ha'isha bemachat hanequvah. A woman cannot go out with a needle that
has a hole in it, has an eye in it, because that
apparently would not be considered a type of clothing, it would be
a way you would carry a needle. You have to carry your
needle because a needle with a hole in it is used for
sewing, so you stick it in your garments, but that's just a
form of carrying. ולא בטבעת שיש עליה חותם, Velo betaba'at sheyeish aleha
chotam, not a ring that has on it a seal, a signet
ring, as we've seen before. The assumption that that's not the norm
for women to wear that, and therefore also it's considered conveyance carrying
around your finger, it is not considered wearing. ולא בכולייר ולא בכובלת,
Velo bekhulyar velo bekhovelt,
and not with a כולייר khulyar or a כובלת. khovelt. The גמרא
Gemara will explain this, but כולייר khulyar is some type of a
clasp, not exactly clear in the גמרא Gemara why it's a problem,
but again we have to assume that somehow this was not considered
the norm. It's not so clear, there's very little discussion on that
we'll see. וכובלת ולא בצלוחית של פלייטון, Vekhovelt velo bitzluchit shel plaiton,
that those two are described as essentially the same thing. A כובלת
khovelt is some type of a little glass little flask that she'd
wear around her neck like a little bottle that had in it
some, you know, sweet smelling incense or, you know, or herbs. And
a bottle of פלייטון plaiton is the same. רש"י Rashi says פלייטון
plaiton is בלסמא, balmsa, משחת האפרסמון. mishchat ha'afarsimon. So, balsam. So, balsam's
a wood though, right?
It could also in the balsam we have here in northern latitudes
is not the balsam of the Torah, the balsam of the Torah
is a bush.
Okay. And does it create some aromatic? Yes. They derive some aromatic
oil from
it?
Yes, one of the things in the קטורת ketoret is usually translated
as balsam.
Okay. So there you have it.
Not the balsam tree that you see.
Got it. So aromatic, some aromatic smelling scent to wear around your
neck. ואם יצתה, Ve'im yatzeta,
and if she went out with any of these, חייבת חטאת, chayavet
chatat, she's obligated a sin offering because these are all considered to
be although again they're on your body, it's not considered wearing them,
it's considered carrying them. דברי ר' מאיר, Divrei Rabi Meir, that's what
Rabbi Meir says. וחכמים פוטרים בכובלת ובצלוחית של פלייטון. Vachachamim potrim bekhovelt
uvetzluchit shel plaiton.
The Rabbis exempt you with these last two cases, this case of
these various flasks that you have in it aromatic herbs or some
aromatic
scent, incense, like, you know, oil. Okay. So that is we've seen
before a ר' מאיר Rabi Meir a discussion of Rabbi Meir and
the חכמים Chachamim if you remember by the עיר של זהב Ir
Shel Zahav where Rabbi Meir was more prepared to consider certain things
carrying and we're going to see that again in the
גמרא. Gemara.
So my question is שחיקת סמנין, shchikat samanim, right? So these are
aromatic things. Is that just for medicine that we're worried about the
grinding things?
No. Oh, that's a good question but I don't want to talk
about that. Whether שחיקת סמנין shchikat samanim can apply to other scenarios
that are not directly medicinal, but anyway, regardless, that would be a
rabbinic issue and here we're dealing biblically whether it's carrying, and you're
not ingesting it and whatever. No, it's not שחיקת סמנין shchikat samanim
that sense you're allowed to smell or put on your body aromatic
incense. It is very specifically about using things in a medicinal way.
So let's take a look at the גמרא, Gemara, that problem. Anyway,
but this is the issue of carrying. So let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר עולא, Amar Ula, so says Ula: וחילופיהן
באיש, Vechilufeihen be'ish,
the reverse is true by a man. What does it mean the
reverse is true by a man? So we're skipping over the needle
with eye in it, that we take for granted, okay, that's carrying,
that's not wearing. But we go to the ring with a signet
on it, a signet ring. And we've already discussed in the גמרא
Gemara that that was less norm for a woman but much more
norm for a man.
Didn't this thing? Right. So doesn't it show that women engaged in
business?
Yes. And we're going to discuss that later as well. They could,
but again it also does show that it was not as much
the norm and certainly not as much the norm for them to
wear it as a type of something worn, maybe to use it
but not to wear it. So anyway, so what Ula says is
that now it's interesting, this says a woman can't wear, you know,
a normal ring it's a rabbinic problem, a signet ring it's a
biblical problem, and the משנה Mishnah never tells you this משנה Mishnah
or any later משנה Mishnah what the story is with a man
wearing these rings. The assumption
that... Actually said that and he goes even further. He says the
reverse is true by a man. What does it mean the reverse
is true by a man? On the one hand, a signet ring
is not a problem, that's the norm, but on the other hand,
a ring without a signet is a problem because that's normally a
woman's what a woman wears, right, talk about wedding rings or whatever.
So he is saying that actually for a man to wear a
non-signet ring is considered to be carrying for a man. It's the
exact reverse of what it is for a woman. And now the
גמרא Gemara looks at this. Before we look at saying of man
a non-signet ring is a problem, it looks at the statement that
says that for a man a signet ring is not an issue.
Now that you would have assumed is implicit in the משנה. Mishnah.
But עולא Ulla is making it more explicit and he's saying the
reverse is true. For a woman signet ring is carrying, for a
man it's not carrying. And let's take a look at what the
גמרא Gemara says about this. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אלמא, Alma, we see כסבר עולא kasavar Ulla that עולא Ulla is
of the opinion כל מידי דחזי לאיש לא חזי לאישה מידי דחזי
לאישה לא חזי לאיש. kol midi dechazi le'ish lo chazi le'isha midi
dechazi le'isha lo chazi le'ish. Now it doesn't mean here everything, of
course like you can have a I don't know a belt, a
shirt, or whatever, but it says there are so I think you
have to read the כל kol here in a little narrower sense,
but it says there are certain types of clothing, this is how
I'll read it, that are basically women's clothing and not men's. And
certain things that are men's and not women's. And because it is
a man's clothing, if you take this type of thing that is
a man's clothing like a signet ring, if a woman wears it,
it's considered carrying, even though for a man it would be clothing.
And you take this other type of thing like a non-signet ring
that for a woman is the norm and is primarily women's clothing,
then if a man were to wear it, it wouldn't be clothing
and it would be considered carrying. Now that sounds very reasonable, right?
Some things are, you know, appropriate for one gender, not for the
other, and if worn by the other gender, maybe seen as bizarre,
maybe even not considered wearing. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't take this
as so obvious. Maybe the גמרא Gemara says if for one gender
it's considered clothing, then even if the other gender wears it, bracketing
any questions of בגד איש beged ish or whatever, that's not our
concern, but if the other gender wears it, it's not carrying, it's
wearing clothing. The very fact that the תורה Torah says לא ילבש
גבר שמלת אשה lo yilbash gever simlat isha means that if a
man is wearing שמלת אשה, simlat isha, it's considered ילבש, yilbash, it's
considered that he's wearing it, not like he's carrying it on the
body. So if a man puts on a dress, he's wearing a
dress, he's not carrying a dress. But עולא Ulla says no, if
you wear something of the other gender, it's considered carrying and not
wearing. So let us take a look. מתיב רב יוסף. Metiv Rav
Yosef. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef asked him this. הרועים, Haro'im, the
shepherds, יוצאים בשקים, yotzim besakim,
can go out with a type of a sackcloth garment. These were
the garments that shepherds would wear, you know, rough and tough and
it would not be, you know, denim essentially, right. And then it
says the תוספתא, Tosefta, ולא הרועים בלבד אמרו, velo haro'im bilvad amru,
not just shepherds, אלא כל אדם, ela kol adam, any anybody actually
if you wear it isn't carrying. אלא שדרכן של רועים לצאת בשקין,
ela shedarkan shel ro'im latzet besakin,
but shepherds are the ones that normally wear these sack garments and
therefore we said shepherds. So why is this a question? It says
look, here's a type of a garment that is only worn by
one group of people, shepherds, and nevertheless if you wear it, it's
considered wearing, not carrying. So why don't we say the same about
a man wearing a woman's garment and vice versa? It's wearing and
not carrying. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא אמר רב יוסף, ela
amar Rav Yosef, so says רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, here כסבר עולא
נשים עם בפני עצמן הן. kasavar Ulla nashim am bifnei atzman hen.
So עולא Ulla holds that women are their own nation. So men
are from Mars and women are from Venus, right? So what the
גמרא Gemara probably means by that, although obviously this could be read
in many ways, but what the גמרא Gemara I assume means by
this, the way I'll interpret it is in a very local meaning,
which is that within clothing, clothing is very gendered. So therefore, if
something that is, you know, if something is worn by some men
and not other men, and a man wears it, or some women
and not other women, and a woman wears it, you're still wearing
clothing, you know, that's your clothing. But when it comes to cross-dressing
essentially, clothing is very gendered and it's like it's a completely foreign
thing. So for a man to wear woman's clothing is much different
than a man to wear a type of a costume or an
outfit only worn by a sub-class of men. And therefore, it's not
legitimately called wearing and it would be carrying, and vice versa for
a woman to wear man's clothing. So that's what עולא Ulla says,
specifically here when you go across gender and you're wearing the different
clothes, that is carrying on שבת, Shabbat, even though for one gender
it's completely considered clothing.
Yes, so if I wear like a גוי'ישע goyishe men's clothing, would
that be... that's literally a different עם, am, but
it would be considered wearing. That's a good question. I would say
no. I mean I would say it would be wearing. I would
say, right, I don't think, you know, what does this mean עם
בפני עצמו, am bifnei atzmo, I think it specifically is about gender
and clothing and I do not think that it's about, you know,
you're right, if something that specifically is like if I go around
wearing a toga, you know, or how about if I wear, you
know, what... right. Yeah, I actually think that it's specifically about clothing
being gendered and not about עם am or that type of an
issue. Yes. Fedora hats.
Fedora hats were a women's style for decades before becoming...
Well things can change. I mean you know, the whole issue about...
No, things change! The whole issue about what בגד איש beged ish
and בגד אשה, beged isha, you know, actually does change over time
because those are sociological categories. But there are periods, you know, where
those lines are being are being sort of violated, you know, being
crossed and it's seen as a type of a cross-dressing and then
it changes, like women wearing pants. You know, so I mentioned it
the other day that that it's rare to find anybody nowadays who
will say, you know, some people obviously, you know, culturally in in
various areas of the community it's seen as off limits and, you
know, people might talk about צניעות, tsniut, but it's much rarer to
find anybody nowadays that's going to make the בגד אשה beged isha
argument by pants because those certain of those realities change over time.
But when they are the things that are still realities, you know,
do, you know, clothing is very gendered. And that I do think
by the way is why, actually we're going to turn to it
in a minute, talking about תפילין, tfillin, that issues around women wearing
טלית talit and תפילין tfillin lead to such like strong reaction because
it for you know because not you know whatever the הלכתי halakhic
arguments are that are raised but it you know at some visceral
level for some people it feels like cross-dressing, feels like women are
you know dressing like a man, there's something very visceral about about
clothing and identity around gender identity. So that's actually what the גמרא
gemara is going to turn to around this issue of תפילין. tfillin.
So let's take a look at this. So the גמרא gemara says
like this. איתיביה אביי, Eitiviah Abaye, אביי Abaye asked on this. המוציא
תפילין, Hamotsi tfillin, if you find תפילין tfillin and you know they're
in the middle of the road and you're afraid they'll get you
know stolen or trampled on שבת. Shabbat. This is שבת, Shabbat, how
do you take them inside if there's no עירוב? eruv? So what
do you do? מכניסן זוג זוג, Makhnisan zug zug, you can go
ahead and put them on a pair at a time, meaning first
the של יד shel yad and the של ראש, shel rosh, wear
them, bring them inside, undo them, go back out if there's multiple
ones, put on again של יד shel yad and של ראש shel
rosh and bring them inside so you're wearing it, okay? אחד איש
ואחד אשה, Ekhad ish ve-ekhad isha, whether a man or a woman.
So a woman can wear it and it's not carrying. Now here
תפילין tfillin is very much normally worn by men and it says
for a woman can wear it on שבת Shabbat and you know
it's not a problem, it's not considered carrying. So you see even
something that normally is worn by men is not considered carrying when
worn by women. ואי אמרת נשים עם בפני עצמן הן, Ve-i amrat
nashim am bifnei atsman hen, and if women are their own nation
and again what I'll say is meaning if when it comes to
clothing there's a real difference women and men and they are not
seen what's clothing for one is not seen as necessarily clothing for
the other. So ומצות עשה שהזמן גרמה הוא, Ve-mitsvat ase she-ha-zman gramah
hu, תפילין tfillin is a time bound מצוה, mitsvah, וכל מצות עשה
שהזמן גרמה נשים פטורות, Ve-khol mitsvat ase she-ha-zman gramah nashim pturot, and
women are exempt and therefore this is not the type of thing
that women wear. And therefore isn't it, why shouldn't it be a
שבת Shabbat problem? So the
גמרא gemara says, התם קסבר רבי מאיר. Hatam kasavar Rabbi Meir. No,
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is of the opinion, because that's רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir who said that previous teaching, לילה זמן תפילין הוא ושבת
זמן תפילין הוא. Laila zman tfillin hu ve-Shabbat zman tfillin hu. That
the two reasons that תפילין tfillin are time bound are because you
don't wear it at night and you don't wear it at שבת.
Shabbat. Well, we will argue, meaning we don't know it but we'll
assert
that
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is of the opinion that you wear שבת
Shabbat at night or you're allowed to wear... I mean you wear
תפילין tfillin at night or you're allowed to and you're allowed to
wear תפילין tfillin on שבת Shabbat and therefore תפילין tfillin is not
time bound. It's every single day, every single, you know, seven days
a week, twenty-four hours a day. And therefore women are obligated. And
since women are obligated, so therefore she can put on תפילין. tfillin.
Now of course it raises interesting questions. What did רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir think? Did he think that women were going around wearing תפילין?
tfillin? I mean was that common, a thing for him that women
wore תפילין? tfillin? Maybe his wife did? Maybe his wife did? Was
he saying that because even if people...
Is there anywhere? Is there?
Well there is a good discussion in the גמרא, gemara, yes, in
ערובין Eruvin there is... well I don't know about רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir particularly or you mean because you're thinking about ברוריה? Bruria? Yeah,
exactly.
The גמרא gemara I have to check. The גמרא gemara in ערובין,
Eruvin, this is a discussion in ערובין Eruvin about finding תפילין tfillin
and wearing them indoors and the גמרא gemara there discusses at greater
length this issue about whether women are obligated in תפילין tfillin and
is it time bound? I have to check there whether the גמרא
gemara actually concludes, you know, that that's a particular position of רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. I have to check. Here it's just asserting it
as a way of reading this ברייתא, brayta, okay, as a you
know, but I I have to check whether that גמרא gemara actually
concludes that in terms of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. But look, it
raises an interesting question which is what...
at least as defined in the מנחות, Menachot, so it's right.
Yeah, but you know, I mean, a little bit. The גמרא's gemara
are interesting that way where the locus of certain things is. The
primary discussion of women and תפילין tfillin is in ערובין Eruvin about
around this issue. Anyway, but here's the question. It's an interest... it's
an interesting thing. Is... presumably I mean, you know, the גמרא gemara
is saying this is his position. But it's not saying that in
רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir's town or whatever all the women wore תפילין.
tfillin. So it's sort of interesting that he's saying like, so he
might have felt, look, everybody is going around following some different פסק,
psak, but since in theory I believe women are obligated in תפילין,
tfillin, therefore I am asserting that this is women's clothes as well.
Which is interesting because the societal norms one imagines were still that
women weren't wearing תפילין. tfillin. One imagines, I mean you could say
otherwise. But anyway, so it's interesting that until now we've been... assuming
that all of this clothing identity is defined by societal norms, and
here it's being defined by הלכה halakhic realities. If women are not
obligated, it's not women's clothes. It's not. It's men's clothing. And if
women are and if women are obligated, it's women's clothing without any
attention to what the societal realities are. Anyway, that's the גמרא's Gemara's
answer. That's why women could wear it. Actually, if women were not
obligated in תפילין, tefillin, you're right, a woman putting on תפילין tefillin
would be carrying on שבת. Shabbat.
So some of this is neutral? Is not הלכה halakhically imperative and
is defined by societal norms?
Presumably, yeah, I mean you have to work that out. So then
the גמרא Gemara is not done. The גמרא Gemara says והא הוצאה
כלאחר יד הוא. ve-ha hotza'ah k'le-achar yad hu. One minute, says the
גמרא, Gemara, I don't get it. So fine, you want to argue
that a woman wearing a man's signet ring is considered carrying for
a woman and not for a man because it's basically men's clothing.
Okay, but even if it is carrying, even if I say that
for a woman it's not considered clothing, but the way you carry
things is you hold it in your palm of your hand. You
don't carry things by putting it on your finger, especially if we're
saying that it's not clothing for you. If we're saying that this
is not something you wear on your finger, so then even if
we say it's not clothing, why are you biblically transgressing? You're carrying
it in an unusual way. You're carrying it on your finger rather
than in your hand. So why would this woman be carrying by
this signet ring? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבי ירמיה, Amar
Rabbi Yirmiyah, here, רבקה, Rivkah, here's what the גמרא Gemara says, באישה
גזברית עסקינן. be-ishah gizbarit askinan.
We're talking about a woman who is a treasurer, a businesswoman. We're
talking about a woman that very
often, you know, uses a signet ring in her business and for
her it is a regular thing to have it on her finger.
So again, interestingly, even if for her it's the norm, what we're
saying is that since socially and more sort of as a group
collectively, men wear it and women don't, so therefore it's still considered
carrying and not wearing. But since it's the norm for her to
be on her finger, it's considered carrying in a normal way. So
what we're saying is that for such
women, this is not clothing for them, but for such women, it's
normal for them to use it and it's normal for them to
carry it on their finger. So for them, it's a normal way
to carry, but it's not clothing. So she—so that type of a
woman is חייבת חטאת. chayevet chatat. Any other woman who would wear
it, it wouldn't be a normal way of carrying, so then she
wouldn't be חייב chayav unless she had it in the palm of
her hand. But for this type of a woman, since she normally
has it on her finger, we're not going to call it clothing,
but we'll call it a normal way of carrying it and she
would be חייבת. chayevet. But for a man? Man, it would not
be a problem because men wear it and it's the norm. Okay,
so אמר רבה, Amar Rabbah, so or אמר רבא, Amar Rava, some
say here, רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Rabbah bar bar
Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, תירצת אישה. teratzta isha. You've explained by the
woman how this signet ring is not wearing and for a certain
type of a woman, it's considered the normal way to carry and
you could transgress biblically שבת. Shabbat. איש מאי איכא למימר? ish mai
ika le-meimar? How about a man wearing a non-signet ring? If you
say that normal rings are women's clothes and not men's, and for
a man it's considered carrying, not wearing, so
why is it biblical? You don't carry things on your finger, you
carry them in the palm of your hand. And if it's not
normal for men to wear rings, then it's an unusual way of
carrying. So why would it be a biblical transgression for man? אלא
אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, rather רבא Rava says let me explain
to you a scenario which explains why it's a normal way of
not wearing, but of carrying for men and for women. פעמים שאדם
נותן לאשתו טבעת שיש עליה חותם. pe'amim she-adam noten le-ishto taba'at she-yesh
aleha chotam.
Sometimes a man takes off his signet ring and gives it to
his wife, להוליכה לקופסה, le-holikhah le-kufsa,
say go bring it home, go put it in my jewelry box
or whatever, in the box, right, keep my stuff. Okay, so he
gives this to his wife to carry. And what does she do?
ומניחתה בידה
עד שתגיע לקופסה. u-manichatah be-yadah ad she-tagia le-kufsa. So yes, sometimes it
is a norm for her to wear, not her own signet ring,
but she's carrying her husband's signet ring. What do you do with
a ring? The easiest way not to lose it is to put
it on your finger. So that is a normal way of carrying
rings. Sometimes you put rings on your finger as a way of
carrying them. ופעמים שהאישה נותנת לבעלה טבעת שאין עליה חותם. u-pe'amim she-ha-ishah
notenet le-ba'alah taba'at she-ein aleha chotam.
Sometimes a woman takes off her rings, gives it to her husband,
non-signet ring, להוליכה אצל אומן לתקן, le-holikhah etzel uman le-taken, to bring
it to a jewelry store craftsperson to fix. Interesting, it doesn't have
the קופסה, kufsa, you would have expected a parallel example, but maybe
those were some degree certain norms and certain realities. So her husband
has to take this ring to the jeweler. So it's his wife's
ring. So what does he do not to forget it? ומניחה בידו
עד שיגיע אצל אומן. u-manichah be-yado ad she-yagia etzel uman. You
put it on your finger, easiest way to carry it and not
to lose it. So you know what? For man and a woman,
the opposite types of rings are not—are not considered clothing, but it
would be considered a normal way of carrying to put it on
your finger. Sometimes that is a way you carry it without losing
it. You put it on your finger, but that does not—so therefore
it's a normal way of carrying, you're obligated a חטאת. chatat. But
just because it's a normal way of carrying does not mean it's
clothing. Since it's identified with the other gender, then for you to
put it on is actually considered to be carrying and not wearing.
So that is a very interesting position. So that is a very
interesting position of עולא *Ulla*, not so clear how do we rule
about that, you know, do we rule that anything that is identified
with another gender when you wear it is defined as carrying and
not clothing? Also what's not clear is that in this the halachic
discussions about women wearing תפילין *tefillin*, this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* by bringing
it into this question of for a woman to wear it it
would be considered carrying not wearing because it's like associated with men
sort of starts suggesting a possibility which some people want to argue
that women wearing תפילין *tefillin* is considered בגד איש *beged ish*, right?
So because if it's once it's identified or a טלית *tallis* or
whatever, yeah, so they change,
right?
For the בגד *beged* specifically around בגד איש *beged ish* or I
understand that people oppose it, but I'm saying the specific בגד איש
*beged ish* argument.
It offends the male sensibilities.
Right. So anyway, I just note that here. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is not having here a discussion of בגד איש *beged ish* and
בגד אישה *beged isha* in terms of the biblical
מצווה *mitzvah*, but it is having it in terms of is it
enough identified that when it's on the other person we won't call
it wearing on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* and we'll call it a form
of carrying. I want to make one other mention about this, which
is not clear in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, which is the debate
between רש"י Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות Tosfos *Tosfos*. עולא *Ulla* says the
reverse. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has been focusing on whether it's considered
biblical carrying, that for a woman to wear a signet ring is
biblical carrying, for a man to wear a non-signet ring is biblical
carrying the exact opposite. What about the rabbinic issues? For a woman
to wear a non-signet ring is a rabbinic problem she might take
it off. What about for a man to wear a signet ring?
We're saying it's not carrying that's normal for it to be for
a man to wear it, is there a rabbinic problem for a
man to wear it? Are we concerned that the man might come
and take it off and show it to his friends? So רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says yes, the same type of rabbinic concerns we have
by a woman we have by a man, and therefore we're concerned
that certain things a man it's not carrying but he might come
to take off and show. Not everything, you're not going to take
off your shirt or your pants or whatever, but things that are
sort of like secondary types of objects and may be very attractive
or whatever you might take off and show and show. But right
רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* says trying to based on other סוגיות *sugyos*
not just סתם *stam*, that he says it actually does not seem
that these rabbinic restrictions were applied to men, that there was the
same concern that men would take off articles of clothing and show
to their friends, maybe that was only a concern for women. So
that's interesting that he says all the things we've been learning you
might take it off and show it, רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* wants
to argue that specifically were said by women's clothing and not by
men's.
What? רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* disagrees.
Right, that's true, but not like to but not to show to
your friend in the middle of the street. Nobody is saying you're
never taking it off, but that type of a common concern of
oh look at this nice thing I've got and inspecting it or
whatever, now that it was not as common by men. That's at
least רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* argues, it is not clear from the
משנה Mishna *Mishnah* or the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
It's a question by regular rings so we're not concerned she's going
to take it off to show her friends?
We are, a regular ring was rabbinic. That's what I said, a
ring with a חותם *chosam* is biblical and a regular ring is
rabbinic.
Right, I mean it still makes sense because okay
so you like רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam*.
So the other thing is so how are we explaining the מחט
נקובה *machat nekuva*? It's a normal way...
We didn't explain, but same idea
that again what is interesting is the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that
you can normally have it on your body and still not be
clothing and that being on your body is a convenient way of
carrying something. The best example, obvious example I gave you was a
knapsack, okay? If you wore a knapsack on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* with
stuff in it, that's completely the normal way that people do it,
but it's not clothes, it's carrying. It's the normal way of carrying
it by being on your body. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
saying the same could be about a woman with a signet ring,
a man with a non-signet ring, the needle with a hole in
it. You don't wear a needle with a hole in it says
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* as jewelry, but you will sometimes stick it
in your clothes as an easy way of carrying so that it
doesn't get
lost. Not כאורחיה *ke'orchayiah*. It's the normal way of carrying, yes.
Why aren't we concerned they're wearing clothing for business on
שבת *Shabbos*?
That's a problem? You mean what? Like the needle with the hole
in it?
Or with the ring with the חותם *chosam*.
We might be, but right now we're talking about הלכות הוצאה *hilchos
hotzaah*, if we want to talk about is it מוקצה *muktzah*, is
it כלי kli, שמלאכתו לאיסור *kli she-melachto l'issur*? So fine we could
talk about that too, but right now we're dealing more with דאורייתא
*de'oraisas* and our focus is הוצאה *hotzaah*. Okay so it doesn't but
you're right there are other issues and we could also have been
talking about the עבירה *aveirah* of בגד איש *beged ish*, you know
that's not our concern right now. Okay so it doesn't I don't
think it's meant to exclude that possibility.
Wait, רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* says that it's מותר mutar. *muttar* to
carry it out.
No, רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* says a man wearing oh you see
the signet ring example. So you're right, that would be specifically by
signet ring, but he has a larger discussion about like all of
these things. But that's a good point, he does say he is
specifically saying it to a signet ring so if he's saying מותר
*muttar* why is he addressing the מוקצה *muktzah* question or whatever? Look,
even a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור *kli she-melachto l'issur* can be worn. more
wearing you know with צורך גופו צורך מקומו tzorech mekomo but it's
a good question like why is he unless he feels that אדרבא
adaraba the fact that the גמרא Gemara saying that it's normal for
men and a type of a clothing means they would also wear
signet rings just as jewelry as well, you know, so I imagine
that that's that's what he would say. That דוקא davka because it
not only has its business identity. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues ולא בכוליאר ולא בכובלת. v'lo b'kulyar v'lo b'koveles. You can't wear—a
woman can't wear this כוליאר kulyar or כובלת koveles and if she
does she might be חייב חטאת. chayav chatas. So, debate of Rabbi
Meir and the חכמים Chachamim by the כובלת. koveles. מאי כוליאר? Mai
kulyar? What is this כוליאר? kulyar? אמר רב Amar Rav or אמר
רבי, Rabbi, I don't know who it is, אמר רב Amar Rav
I guess, מכבנתא. machbenasa. So what's a מכבנתא? machbenasa? So רש"י rashi
says it's some type of a clasp to hold a garment together
which of course makes you think that it would be totally clothing
so I really don't know why and I didn't find too much
discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim why this is—first of all, what is
a מכבנתא machbenasa is not clear, and number two, why it's not
considered clothing. But the גמרא Gemara now turns its attention to כובלת.
koveles. So let's take a look. כובלת, Koveles, what's a כובלת? koveles?
אמר רב, Amar Rav, חומסא דפילון, chumsa d'pilon, a type of a
bundle of herbs or spices again for perfume, for nice smelling. Okay,
so it's very similar to the other case in the משנה Mishna
of the צלוחית של פלייטון tzlochis shel palyaton which is the little
bottle of this balsam oil. So, now this is debated between Rabbi
Meir and the חכמים. Chachamim. So the גמרא Gemara says and וכן
אמר רב אסי חומסא דפילון, v'chen amar Rav Assi, chumsa d'pilon, okay,
this bundle of spices. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, coming in here, or
the ברייתא Baraisa teaches לא תצא בכובלת ואם יצאה חייבת חטאת
דברי רבי מאיר. lo seitzei b'koveles, v'im yatza chayaves chatas, divrei Rabbi
Meir. Rabbi Meir says that if she wears this little perfume bottle
around her neck it's biblical carrying. וחכמים אומרים לא תצא, V'chachamim omrim,
lo seitzei, don't go out, but it's only rabbinic, ואם יצאה פטורה
v'im yatza ptura if she goes out she's exempt and the גמרא
Gemara. will explain why. רבי אליעזר אומר יוצאה אשה בכובלת לכתחילה. Rabbi
Eliezer omer, yotza isha b'koveles l'chatchila.
She can go out no problem. If you remember it's the exact
same three opinions and debate about the עיר של זהב, ir shel
zahav, about the golden tiara. חייב חטאת, Chayav chatas, אסור דרבנן, assur
d'rabanan,
מותר. So the same type of thing still exists today by a
lot of שבת שאלות. Shabbos shailas. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says
let's take a
look, opening bottles on שבת, חייב חטאת, chayav chatas, אסור. assur. Anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this, ובמאי קמיפלגי? u'v'mai kamifligi? What's
the debate? רבי מאיר סבר משאוי הוא. Rabbi Meir savar massui hu.
It is a burden, not telling us why it's a burden. Presumably,
look, it's not clothing, it's not there maybe for ornament, for attractiveness,
it's there so the woman smells nice. That's a way of carrying
it. You carry it around the neck so you smell nice at
all times but it's not something you wear. Again, exactly what's defined
as wearing versus carrying on your body is partly the issue. So
that's what Rabbi Meir says. Maybe he would also say it's not
the norm, most women don't do it, so maybe that has something
to do with it. ורבנן סברי תכשיט הוא. V'rabanan savri tachshit hu.
No, it's a form of jewelry. So why is it rabbinically an
issue? ודילמא שלפה ומחויא ואתי לאתויי, V'dilma shalfa u'machvya v'asa l'asuye, the
standard concern she'll take it off and show a friend and she'll
come to carry it four אמות. amos. Yeah and look why didn't—smell
it, see how beautiful it smells. ורבי אליעזר סבר, V'Rabbi Eliezer savar,
Rabbi Eliezer
holds no, מאן דרכו—remember man darko by the עיר של זהב ir
shel zahav the rabbis were afraid the woman would take off the
tiara and Rabbi Eliezer says no, no, only very high status women
wear a gold tiara, they don't take things off in the public.
So let's see what he says about this aromatic bottle. So he
says מאן דרכו למירימי? man darko l'miremei? Who—whose—is
it normally the type of person who wears this perfume bottle around
her neck? אשה שריחה רע, Isha she'reicha ra, a woman with bad
odor. So אשה שריחה רע לא שלפה ומחויא. isha she'reicha ra lo
shalfa u'machvya.
So a woman with bad odor doesn't want to take the perfume
bottle off of her body ולא אתי לאתויי ארבע אמות ברשות הרבים.
v'lo asa l'asuye arba amos b'reshus harabim. She won't take it off,
she won't come to carry. Now again תוספות says this doesn't mean
we're making a different הלכה halacha for different types of women, but
what we're doing is we're saying which types of objects. So objects
that are not normally a problem because of certain societal realities, those
are not problematic and these perfume bottles are not problematic for anybody.
So the גמרא Gemara says והא תניא, ve'ha tanya, we taught in
the ברייתא, Baraisa, רבי אליעזר פוטר בכובלת ובצלוחית של פלייטון. Rabbi Eliezer
poter b'koveles u'v'tzlochis shel palyaton. That Rabbi Eliezer says you're exempt but
presumably not that it's allowed לכתחילה. l'chatchila. So the גמרא Gemara says
לא קשיא, lo kashya, that's not difficult. הא כקאי דרבי מאיר, Ha
k'kaya d'Rabbi Meir, when he's arguing with Rabbi Meir then he'll say
Rabbi Meir says חייב, chayav, he says פוטר poter and not חייב,
chayav, no you're exempt. הא כקאי דרבנן, Ha k'kaya d'rabbanan, when he's
arguing with the rabbis, the rabbis say don't do it לכתחילה, l'chatchila,
he says you're allowed to do it לכתחילה. l'chatchila. So he holds
consistently you can do it לכתחילה, l'chatchila, he just doesn't always articulate
that because first he has to argue with Rabbi Meir who says
you're חייב. chayav. So the גמרא gemara says כי קאי דרבי מאיר
דאמר חייב חטאת, ki kaya d'Rabbi Meir d'amar chayav chatas, when he's
in Rabbi Meir's area saying you're חייב חטאת, chayav chatas, אמר ליה
amar lei he says back to him פוטר, poter, no you're not
חייב חטאת, chayav chatas, you're exempt. כי קאי דרבנן דאמרי פוטר אבל
אסור Ki kaya d'rabbanan d'amri poter aval assur when he's talking to
the rabbis who say you're exempt but it's rabbinically forbidden אמר איהו
מותר לכתחילה. amar ihu mutar l'chatchila. He says it's permissible לכתחילה. l'chatchila.
Wow, look at the next
דף, daf, right? So you—ומאי רבי מאיר, u'mai Rabbi Meir, where do
you see that Rabbi Meir and Rabbi Eliezer debate this type of
Exactly, we've had a ברייתא beraita that it was a three-way debate.
Where do you see that it was ever framed as a two-way
debate? דתניא, di-tanya, we taught a ברייתא, beraita, לא תצא אשה במפתח
שבידה, lo tetze ishah b'mafte'ach she-b'yadah, a woman can't go and carry
her her her key in her hand, there you go, the biggest
issues when there's no עירוב eruv is carrying your key. What, a
woman? Right. ואם יצאת חייבת חטאת דברי רבי מאיר, ve-im yatzatah chayavet
chatat divrei Rabbi Meir, and if she goes out she's חייבת חטאת,
chayavet chatat, that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. רבי אליעזר פוטר
בקובלת ובצלוחית של פלייטון. Rabbi Eliezer poter b'koveles u-v'tzlochit shel plyton. But
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer exempts when you're dealing with a perfume bottle.
So the גמרא gemara says, קובלת מן דכיר שמיה? koveles man dachir
shemeih? Who's talking about a perfume bottle? We're talking about carrying your
keys. So the גמרא gemara says, חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני, chasuri mechasra
ve-hachi katani, clearly there's some words missing and here's what it needs
to read. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says if you carry your key
you're חייב חטאת, chayav chatat, וכן בקובלת וכן בצלוחית של פלייטון, ve-chen
b'koveles ve-chen b'tzlochit shel plyton, and similarly if you have a perfume
bottle around your neck, לא תצא ואם יצאת חייבת חטאת דברי רבי
מאיר, lo tetze ve-im yatzatah chayavet chatat divrei Rabbi Meir, that's what
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. רבי אליעזר פוטר בקובלת ובצלוחית של פלייטון.
Rabbi Eliezer poter b'koveles u-v'tzlochit shel plyton. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
doesn't debate the key, but regarding the perfume bottle, there he exempts,
and as we've seen, not only he exempts, he actually says it
is permissible. Okay. במה דברים אמורים, bameh devarim amurim, when is that
true that according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer it's permissible, according to
the רבנן Rabanan at least it's only a rabbinic issue, כשיהיה בה
בוסם, keshe-yehei bah bosem,
if there is actually some of that aromatic oil in it. So
then it's doing its
function. אבל אין בה בוסם, aval ein bah bosem, if
it doesn't
have the aromatic
oil, חייבת, chayavet, שתיחייב. she-techayev. אמר רב אדא בר אהבה, amar Rav
Adda bar Ahava, זאת אומרת, zot omeret, this
tells you, המוציא אוכלין פחות
מכשיעור בכלי חייב. ha-motzi ochlin pachos m'k'shiur b'kli chayav.
That if you take out of food in a vessel less than
the minimum amount of food, you're חייב. chayav. Now what does that
mean? It's a debate later in the גמרא. Gemara There's a minimum
amount of food to take out on שבת you're חייב, chayav, a
ככותבת, k'kosevet, whatever, certain size. So let's say I have half of
the minimum. I have, I don't know, a half a grape. So
if I were to take a half a grape out into רשות
הרבים, reshut ha-rabim, I'd be exempt, I did not take a full
minimum size.
Let's
say I put my half a grape in a bowl and I
take that out to רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabim. Now if I just
took the bowl out, I'd be חייב. chayav. A bowl is a
significant thing. But maybe if I take out a half a grape
in a bowl, I'm exempt. Why? Because when I'm taking out a
half of a grape in a bowl, the point isn't the bowl.
If you have food in a כלי, the point is the food.
So therefore it's not considered like I'm taking out a bowl, it's
just considered like I'm taking out a grape. And since I'm taking
out only a half a grape, I'm exempt. I'll tell you where
this plays out. It plays out with issues talking about when there's
no עירוב eruv and so on, about somebody, you know, like pushing
the kid in the stroller. Because, you know, kids might not be
a problem of carrying because חי נושא את עצמו. chai nosei es
atzmo. But what about the stroller? I mean, that's still rabbinic issues,
whatever, I'm not giving any פסק psak in here. But what about
the stroller? No, because the stroller is totally טפל tafel to the
kid. So you're not חייב chayav for because it's not considered carrying
the stroller, it's carrying the kid through the stroller. So that's what
the גמרא Gemara says. It seems from here, though, that you would
be חייב chayav with the half a grape in the bowl. Why?
Because it considers that the although the bottle doesn't have actually the
aromatic oil in it, it still has the fragrance, some of the
fragrance is trapped. And it considers the fragrance like the half grape.
So it's saying, look, why is this woman wearing this bottle? Because
she still wants the fragrance even though there's no oil in it.
So there she is, she's taking out the half of the grape,
but she's taking out
the fragrance without. So Gemara says that let's finish this, דהא deha
here it draws to makes the explicit comparison, אין בה בושם ein
bah bosem if there's no actual aromatic oil in it, פחות מכשיעור
בכלי דמי, pachot mikashiur b'kli dami, it's like the half of the
grape in the vessel. And דתניא חייבת, detanya chayyevet, you're saying she's
חייב chayyav for wearing this bottle without the oil in it. So
רב אשי אמר Rav Ashi amar no, באלמא אימא לך פטור, b'alma
eima lach patur, I'll tell you in the normally like the half
grape example you see you're exempt, that there the vessel is secondary
to the food and you're not חייב chayyav for the food so
you're fully
exempt. ושני הכא v'shani hacha here it's different, דלית ליה ממשא כלל,
d'leit leh mamasha klal, it's not just a half of a grape.
There's no oil at all. So you can't say the vessel is
secondary to fragrance. Fragrance is not a physical thing. So therefore when
all you have, even though she might be wearing it to trap
for the sake of the fragrance, when there's nothing physical then you're
carrying the bottle, there's no question. So the half of a grape
maybe we say it's like carrying the grape, but when there's no
oil, just fragrance, then you're carrying the bottle and then it's a
problem. Yes Michael.
Curious as to why we have to start this, but let's let's
say אישה ומפתח בידה, isha u'mafteach beyada, is that not kind of
obvious?
I don't know, again, maybe the, I don't know. Yes.
Isn't it possible that she's wearing it as jewelry the way that
we talked about a watch that's not working?
Yeah, but the גמרא Gemara assumes not that way. The גמרא Gemara
assumes that these bottles or whatever would not be worn as jewelry
just for their own aesthetic value. The only norm to wear them
is for when they're carrying this perfume in them.
Then why would she have put it on?
Maybe she forgot to take it off, maybe she's trying to get
some of the, like I said, some of the fragrance remains even
though the oil isn't there, it's not as powerful. But again, what
I think is very important and this is going to play out
in terms of the issue of medical issues as well, of bandages
and salves and all of that, is that jewelry does not just
mean nice aesthetic attractive things. Jewelry is like a broad category of
things that we say it's considered wearing these things and not carrying
them on your body. And so medical issues that you always want
and things like bandages you always want on your body, that's connected
to your body. And so here, at least other than רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir who's much more strict, you know, even something that you're
wearing for fragrance, you always want it on your body and therefore
it's considered connected to your body and it's not considered carrying, it's
considered wearing. That's the category of תכשיט. tachshit. Okay, so now it
is a little frustrating that the גמרא Gemara never discusses the abstract
criteria, right? It deals with a lot of specifics, this is a
תכשיט, tachshit, this isn't, this is, this isn't, you have to just
try to figure out what type of criteria is it operating with.
Okay, now because we're talking about nice fragrances and whatever and women
wearing them, we're going to have a little bit of an אגדתא
agadata digression which you could probably guess given the shape of the
דף. daf. So let's take a look. וראשית שמנים ימשחו, v'reishit shemanim
yimshachu, they will anoint themselves with the choicest of oils. This is
a פסוק pasuk from עמוס Amos where עמוס Amos is criticizing the
people that they ignore what the נביאים nevi'im tell them, they ignore
listening to God's word and they just indulge in all of these
physical pleasures. Okay, and they turn a deaf ear to the words
of the prophets. So it says וראשית שמנים ימשחו, v'reishit shemanim yimshachu,
they will anoint themselves with the choicest of oils. So which is
the choicest? So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel, זה פלייטון, zeh pilyaton, this is this balsam oil that we've
been talking about, that's the choicest of oils. מתיב רב יוסף, metiv
Rav Yosef, Rav Yosef asked on this, that to say that this
is the choicest of all oils. We said in סוטה, Sotah, in
the תוספתא, Tosefta, אף על פלייטון גזר רבי יהודה בן בבא ולא
הודו לו. af al pilyaton gazar Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava v'lo hodu
lo. There's a whole list of things that they said after the
חורבן Churban they did not want people to be doing as a
זכר לחורבן, zecher l'Churban, overly indulging. Okay, it was, you know, certain
issues about wearing actually interesting things about brides wearing certain jewelry and
so on. So yeah, well, right. And maybe not just going to
sleep with music. Anyway, so it says that רבי יהודה בן בבא
Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava wanted to forbid this oil, this פלייטון pilyaton
oil, but they didn't agree to him. So what's the question? ואי
אמרת משום תענוג, v'ee amrat mishum ta'anug, if this פלייטון pilyaton oil
is the like this most very indulgent thing, you know, this pleasurable
indulgent thing which the פסוק pasuk is referring to, אמאי לא הודו
לו, amai lo hodu lo, why didn't they agree with him? It
must be that it's more of a basic need and they didn't
want to forbid it. But if it's such an indulgence, why not
forbid it? So אמר ליה אביי, amar leh Abaye, so Abaye said
back, ולטעמיך, u'l'ta'ameich,
according to you, you think anything mentioned in the פסוק pasuk should
have been forbidden, you know, should be proof of it being an
indulgence and should be forbidden? So let's look continue to look at
the פסוק. pasuk. השותים במזרקי יין, hashotim b'mizrekei yayin, those who drink
wine in a מזרק. mizrak. What's a מזרק? mizrak? So רב אמי
ורב אסי, Rav Ami v'Rav Assi, so they debate what this מזרק
mizrak is. חד אמר כניסכנין, chad amar knisknin, which רש"י Rashi says
is some type of like of a glass of a glass long
tube or vessel that has mouths and openings at both ends and
people would drink from it, you know, together, you could multiple drink-o-
could drink from this vessel. וחד אמר שמזרקים כוסותיהן זה לזה, v'chad
amar shemazrikim kosoteihen zeh lazeh,
that actually they would sort of like juggle, you know, their cups
filled with wine. That's got to be a real trick. Anyway, but
some type... type of a thing that they would do that would
just be a total indulgence. Anyway, הכא נמי דאסור hacha nami de-assur
will you tell me that using this קניסקנין kniskanin according to one
of them should be forbidden because here it's listed as an indulgent
way of drinking wine? ורבה בר בר הונא איקלע לבי ריש גלותא
ve-Rabba bar Bar Huna ikla levei Reish Galuta Rabba bar Bar Huna
came to the house of the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta which as
we've seen before is right weren't always the best practices but nevertheless
ושתה בקניסקנין ולא אמר ליה ולא מידי veshata be-kniskanin velo amar leh
velo midi and he saw that the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta presumably
was drinking out of this קניסקנין kniskanin and he didn't say anything,
he didn't say we're not supposed to do that. Now there might
be other reasons you don't want to tell the ריש גלותא Reish
Galuta that what he's doing is wrong, but okay, you see that
it's not a problem. Not everything mentioned in this פסוק pasuk is
forbidden. אלא ela here's the difference. Here's what things are off-limits after
the חורבן הבית. churban habayis. כל מידי דאית ביה תענוג ואית ביה
שמחה, kol midi d'is beh taanug v'is beh simcha, not only an
indulgent, anything that's both a physical indulgence and joyous, then גזרו בה
רבנן, gazru beh rabanan, that is too much after the חורבן churban
that you don't do. אבל מידי דאית ביה תענוג ולית ביה שמחה,
aval midi d'is beh taanug v'leis beh simcha, something that's just a
physical indulgence but it's not about joy, לא גזרו רבנן, lo gazru
rabanan, that's not a problem. The problem is having too much joy
and indulgence at the same time. That's what's off-limits. Certainly they didn't
want to forbid all joy, but what's more, so it's only a
joy that's also connected with indulgence and physical indulgence. But the interesting
thing is they also weren't interested in forbidding physical indulgence. You know
it's only the combination of the two. And that's important by the
way, because you know there are questions that come up like during
ספירה sefira and whatever, is this okay, is that okay, and so
on. And you know people somehow assume that like anything that's pleasurable
is what's forbidden. You know, questions about I don't know, going to
a movie and this and that, like there's a strong practice that
you can't go to a movie during ספירה. sefira. I got to
tell you, nowhere in שולחן ערוך shulchan aruch does it say you
can't go to a movie during ספירה. sefira. But you know, maybe
it's because we don't have as much about the, you know, about
the live music types of things, although plenty of people go to
live music at other times. Anyway, so it's something that's very noticeable
and obvious that you should give up during this time period, you
know, as a זכר לחורבן. zecher l'churban. But technically speaking, I think,
you know, maybe thirty years ago it was different. Like going to
a movie was a big event. You know, now, I mean, with
so overwhelmed with all of the, you know, million channels and whatnot,
that it's a type of a pleasure, it's a תענוג taanug maybe,
you know, it's a slightly more entertaining than watching something on cable.
I mean, there are exceptions to it. Some people go to watch
six hours of Lawrence of Arabia, I don't know, but anyway. But
so anyway, so it's important to know the difference between things that
are about pleasure and things that are about joy. And here the
issues around חורבן churban and אבלות avelus and so on are about
things around joy, not things around pleasure. That's what the גמרא Gemara
says very quickly.
You know, then you can't, let's say, have a Viennese table at
a wedding, right? Because that's pleasurable and joyous, right?
All right, so when we get to סוטה sotah we'll discuss the
exact parameters, yes.
Well, I have known so many people who've gotten married during the
time of ספירה sefira and have...
All right, we are not talking about... Moving on. והשוכבים ve-hashochvim we
continue to read the פסוק. pasuk. השוכבים על מיטות שן, hashochvim al
mitot shen, so this is again a critique of the people that
they are so indulgent and they again they don't listen to the
prophets. השוכבים על מיטות שן, hashochvim al mitot shen, so they lie
down on marble, not marble, ivory couches, you know, to eat, וסרוחים
על ערסותם, useruchim al arsotam,
and they are סרוח saruach on their divan, on their beds, on
their couches. So what does סרוח saruach mean? It could mean like
spread out, but let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara
explains it. The גמרא Gemara, reads it as like סרחון sirchon which
means like stench. So let's take a look. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי
חנינא מלמד שהיו משתינין מים בפני מיטותיהן ערומים. amar Rabbi Yosi berabbi
Chanina melamed shehayu mashtinin mayim bifnei mitoteihen arumim.
They would urinate in front of their beds naked. Now רש"י Rashi
says why naked? It just means that since you're naked when you're
sleeping, so you don't want to go walking around naked or getting
dressed to go to the bathroom. So when you wake up in
the middle of the night, you just urinate right by your bed.
Okay, and that's that they, that they like, you know, make a
stench by their bed. So מגדף בה רבי אבהו. megadef beh Rabbi
Abbahu. רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu like literally cursed him, I mean like
mocked this response, at this interpretation. He said אי הכי, ei hachi,
if so, if that's what the issue is, היינו דכתיב, hainu d'ichtiv,
how do you explain the end of these פסוקים, pesukim, meaning it's
building up that the people are doing all of these indulgences, and
what's the climax? לכן עתה יגלו בראש גולים. lachen ata yiglu berosh
golim.
Now therefore you will go into exile at the head of the
exiles, you know, therefore you're all going to, all of this will
be stripped from you, you'll go to exile because in exchange for
your indulging in these things and not repairing your ways. So how
does that connect to urinating by your bed? That's not about an
indulgence. משום דמשתינין מים בפני מיטותיהן ערומים יגלו בראש גולים? mishum demashtinin
mayim bifnei mitoteihen arumim yiglu berosh golim?
Because they urinate in front of the bed, I'm not saying it's
right to do, but that doesn't connect in the פסוק, pasuk, it
doesn't explain the point about going into exile. Here we're talking about
indulgences, we're not just some talking about inappropriate act, you know, practice.
אלא אמר רבי אבהו, ela amar Rabbi Abbahu, so what does it
mean? Says רבי אבהו, Rabbi Abbahu, אלו בני אדם שהיו אוכלים ושותים
זה עם זה. elu benei adam shehayu ochlim veshotim zeh im zeh.
They would lie down like, you know, next together, you know, because
you would eat on these, you know, like you would recline when
you were eating on these couches, so they would... eat and drink
next to one another, ודובקין מטותיהן זו בזו, u'dovkin mitoseihen zu be'zo,
and they would actually put their beds up against one another side
by side. And then they're so comfortable there, they're side by side
with their beds, ומחליפין נשותיהן זה עם זה, u'machlifin nishoseihen zeh im
zeh, so they would exchange, they would swap wives, ומסריחין ערסותם, u'masrichin
arsotam,
and they would therefore create a stench in their beds בשכבת זרע
שאינו שלהן be'shichvas zera she'eino shelahen with semen that is not their
own. So because they would be sleeping with one another's wives, that
means to be stenching up their bed. So it's basically an allusion,
if you read it as stench and not as spreading out on
their bed, it's a way of saying like sexual sin that emerges
from indulgence, from this overly physically indulgent behaviors, and therefore it's also
relating to this sexual sin, but then it connects to the end
of the
פסוק pasuk of going into exile. אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abbahu,
so now רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu says, the same רבי אבהו, Rabbi
Abbahu, ואמרי לה במתניתא תנא, v'amri lah b'masnisa tana, and something we
taught in a בריתא. braisah. Now this is interesting, the same רבי
אבהו Rabbi Abbahu that said that that's not פשט peshat in the
פסוקים, pesukim, now he is going to talk about the problem of
urinating in front of your bed. ג' דברים מביאין אדם לידי עניות,
Gimmel devarim mevi'in adam lidei aniyut, three things bring a person into
poverty, ואלו הן, v'elu hen, and these are they: המכשתין מים בפני
מטתו ערום, hamashkin mayim bifnei mitaso arom, if you urinate in a
room, if you urinate naked in front of your bed, I'll talk
about it in a minute, ומזלזל בנטילת ידים, u'mezalzel b'netilas yadayim, if
you treat lightly, you denigrate the washing of hands, ושאשתו מקללתו בפניו,
ve'she'ishto mekallalto be'fanav,
and a woman and if a man's wife curses him in his
presence. So now let's see, I'll talk about it why, well I'll
just say what רש"י Rashi says and then I'll say my commentary
after we read it a little bit. רש"י Rashi just says that
the שד shed or whatever, the demon
that brings about
poverty, is drawn after
smelly
things, so stench. So therefore the urine is a stench, or the
hands aren't washed, so therefore they're stenchy, they're not clean. I don't
exactly get the wife issue, but that's at least what רש"י Rashi
says. I'll tell you my read in a minute, but very much
reading it about some like in a metaphysical way about this שד
shed of poverty. So let's take a look. So let's take a
look what the גמרא Gemara says. המכשתין מים בפני מטתו ערום. Hamashkin
mayim bifnei mitaso arom. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so in regarding urinating
naked in front of your bed, says רבא, Rava, לא אמרן אלא
דהדר אפיה לפוריא, lo amran ella d'hadar appei l'purya, that's only if
you're facing the bed. So the urine is getting maybe on the
sheets and right at the bed. לבראי, L'varai, his back is to
the bed, even if you're standing by your bed, but if you're
urinating away from your bed, לית לן בה, lais lan bah, that's
not a problem. ודהדר אפיה לפוריא נמי לא אמרן, V'dehadar appei l'purya
nami lo amran,
and even when you're facing your bed it's not a problem, אלא
לארעא, ella l'ara, only if you do it on the ground because
then again it makes the ground right by your bed absorbs urine,
it becomes smelly. אבל במנא, Aval b'mana, but if you do it
into a vessel, like into a chamber pot, and then you remove
it, לית לן בה, lais lan bah, that's not a problem. So
it's really only a problem when you create the stench, lasting stench
around your bed. ומזלזל בנטילת ידים, U'mezalzel b'netilas yadayim, how about denigrating
washing of the hands? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, לא אמרן אלא דלא
משי ידיה כלל, lo amran ella d'lo mashi yadeih klal, only talking
that you didn't wash your hands at all. אבל משי ולא משי,
Aval mashi v'lo mashi, if you wash them but not well, like
my children or one of them, לית לן בה, lais lan bah,
it's not a problem. Go wash your hands! I did, I heard
the water running! I touched my hands to the water anyway! Then
it's not a problem. Now רש"י Rashi says this doesn't, now the
מהרש"א Maharsha says it doesn't necessarily mean you're יצא ידי נטילת ידים.
yatza yidei netilas yadayim. רש"י Rashi tries to say you have the
bare minimum for נטילת ידים. netilas yadayim. מהרש"א Maharsha says we're not
talking about the הלכה halacha of נטילת ידים. netilas yadayim. We're talking
about cleanliness. So even if you're not, the issue isn't whether you're
יצא yatza or not. The issue is as long as there's some
degree of cleanliness. It's not like you walk out of the bathroom
and you don't wash your hands at all. As long as to
some degree you're doing it, it's not a problem. So the גמרא
Gemara says, but the גמרא rejects this. ולאו מילתא היא, V'lav milta
hi, it's not, that's not true. דאמר רב חסדא, Damar Rav Chisda,
for רב חסדא Rav Chisda said, אנא משאי מלא חפנאי מיא, ana
mashai m'lo chafnai maya, I wash my hands the full, my full
fist of water, meaning totally get water all the way up to
my wrists. ויהבו לי מהשמים מלא חפני טיבותא, V'yehavu li me'hashamayim m'lo
chafnai tivuta, and as a result they give to me from heaven
a
open palms of goodness. Like so I do it with my full
hand and therefore I get a full handbreadth, a full of
reward from heaven. So you see that it's not that if you
only wash your hands a little bit you're only going to get
a little bit of money. So it's not like it's not like
a little bit covers you, you got to wash your hands
well. And finally, ושאשתו מקללתו בפניו, ve'she'ishto mekallalto be'fanav, a man whose
wife curses him in his presence. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, על עסקי
תכשיטיה, al iskei tachshiteha, tying it back to our discussion about jewelry,
that she basically is upset that she wants him to buy her
jewelry and he's not doing
it. והני מילי דאית ליה ולא עביד, V'hanei mili de'is lei v'lo
avid, and that's only a problem if he has the money and
he's not actually spending it. Now the
מהרש"א Maharsha says of course he has money, because we're saying that
this makes you poor. So if it makes you poor it means
right now you're not poor. So the מהרש"א Maharsha says yes, but
what we really mean is that he has enough money that this
is not an unreasonable expenditure and he still refuses to do it,
and therefore it brings to
poverty. Now again, there's... How this connects, you could try to read
this as some type of a shade or whatever. I would like
to suggest that all these three things are basically like showing lack
of respect. Lack of respect to yourself, urinating by your bed, creating
the environment in which you sleep, lack of respect to food, that
you're not washing your hands and you're handling food when you're dirty,
and lack of respect to the other, again, one's wife. So therefore
this is something that he wants and also
as a way of
for her own feeling of what's appropriate for her to be wearing.
When the גמרא discusses כבוד, kavod, כיבוד אב ואם, kibbud av va'em,
one of the first lists of כבוד kavod is that you take
care of somebody's clothing needs, which is an issue of dignity and
so on and therefore you're just being מזלזל mezalzel bah, you're treating
yourself in being מזלזל mezalzel in your own כבוד, kavod, being מזלזל
mezalzel in other people's כבוד. kavod. So I think that's clearly the
theme. Why that leads to poverty, not exactly sure. You could speak
about a type of a sort of not monetary poverty but a
poverty in terms of how we value one another. You could also
say that there's a connection. If you don't respect yourself and you
don't respect others, maybe that has some implications about how much you're
working at earning money, but I have a little hard time to
sort of make connect the dots, yes.
It's also like a stinginess like withholding or a miserliness in each
one of those.
Oh that's even in the urinating? I guess in the washing.
Like why wouldn't you just take the extra time? That's what I...
Aha.
So that's certainly in those last two, but even
in that one you could...
that's a stinginess. But again one wonders like so then is the
poverty is it like a מידה כנגד מידה? mida k'neged mida? That's
how you see. Meaning right, not like there's a clear rational explanation
but like if you're being so stingy then it'll be withheld from
you and I guess you're right that really is brought out by
this thing about I wash my full hands and I get the
full goodness. So that's a nice explanation as well. I guess so.
All right, let's go a little further. דרש רבא בריה דרב עילאי,
Darash Rava brei d'Rav Ilai, מאי דכתיב mai d'ichtiv so רבא Rava
explained what is meant by the פסוק. pasuk. So again we're going
back to we quoted all this thing about indulging in all of
these things and going into גלות galus that was presumably even talking
about men but we're also in the larger context of women and
jewelry and fragrance so you'll see therefore it introduces the next looking
at these פסוקים. pesukim. What is meant by the following פסוקים pesukim
in ישעיהו Yeshayahu also about גלות? galus? ויאמר ה' Vayomer Hashem and
God says, יען כי גבהו בנות ציון ya'an ki gavhu benot Tzion
because the daughters of Zion have been haughty and will now explain
each section of the פסוק. pasuk. So what does that mean? שהיו
מהלכות בקומה זקופה. shehayu mehalchot b'koma zkufa. They would walk in like
an upright bearing, in a haughty
bearing, very erect. Then the פסוק pasuk continues, ותלכנה נטויות גרון vatelachna
netuyot garon and they go with outstretched neck, שהיו מהלכות עקב בצד
גודל. shehayu mehalchot eikev b'tzad godel.
They would walk very
daintily, putting a heel right by the toe, heel by the toe,
not taking big steps but walking very slowly daintily and therefore רש"י
Rashi says in a well it's haughty like it's in a way
of calling it רש"י Rashi understands like it's being the פסוק pasuk
what it's affective, it's seductive, it's a way of calling attention to
oneself and so on. So by the way I should say רש"י
says that this is talking about married women. So I don't know
if it's clear in the פסוקים, pesukim, but obviously that's even more
problematic because then it leads to adultery, but גמרא doesn't make that
comment. Anyway, ומשקרות עינים umesakrot einayim
and they sort of glance with their eyes, דהוו מלו כוחלא לעינייהו
dehavi malyan kouchla l'eineihu so the גמרא explains that they would put
like eyeshadow in their eyes, ומרמזן umeramzan and they would like wink
at people to be men to seduce them. הלוך וטפוף haloch v'tafof
walking in like sort of like
I don't even know how to translate.
Yitzi translated as floating.
Floating. Okay, שהיו מהלכות ארוכות בצד קצרות. shehayu mehalchot arukot b'tzad ktzarot.
Tall women would walk next to small women so it would look
like they would be like floating above, a head above. It's good
for the tall women. I don't know what it did for the
short women. But anyway, okay, וברגליהם תעכסנה uvragleihem te'achasna and with their
legs they will תעכסנה te'achasna so we're going to read that we'll
see how we read that as a word having to do with
like the poison of an adder. I don't know how they read
the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk there basically spew venom. Okay,
spew venom which is exactly what the גמרא is going to say.
אמר רב יצחק דבי רבי אמי, Amar Rav Yitzchak d'bei Rabbi Ami,
מלמד שמטילות
מור ואפרסמון melamed shematilot mor v'afarsimon so we were talking about fragrances
to get rid of bad body odor. Here you're talking about perfume
specifically to be seductive. They would put
מור ואפרסמון, mor v'afarsimon, another very fragrant fragrance, במנעליהם bimnaleihem in their
shoes, ומהלכות בשוקי ירושלים umehalchot b'shukei Yerushalayim
they would go in the marketplaces of Jerusalem, וכיון שמגיעות אצל בחורי
ישראל vecheivan shemagiot etzel bachurei Yisrael and when they would come to
the young men in Israel, בועטות בקרקע boatot bakarka
they would kick the ground, ומתיזות עליהם umatizot aleihem
and the fragrance would sort of get splatter on them, they would
smell some of this fragrance of the perfume, ומכניסות בהן יצר הרע
כארס בכעוס umachnisot bahen yetzer hara k'eres b'achus
and it would enter into them the יצר הרע, yetzer hara, the
evil inclination, like the poison of an adder. So the way they
would walk would be would put this poison into the men and
to seduce men.
These are all married women doing this.
This is what רש"י says, married
women. So מאי פורענותיהם, mai puraniyoteihem, what is their, you know, punishment?
כדרש רבא בר עולא. kidrash Raba bar Ulla. So he explains. It's
so funny, I mean really this is just a pretty straightforward interpretation
of a פסוק, pasuk, right? I mean it a little bit adds
a little color, whatever, but basically it's what the פסוקים psukim are
saying. So here's what he says. It's really the next, the פסוק
pasuk continues. והיה תחת בשם מק, v'haya tachat bosem mak,
in the place
of, of, like fragrance will be מק. mak. So what does he
say מק mak means? מקום
שהיו מתבשמות, makom shehayu mitbasmot, the place that they used to put
the fragrance on, בוא נעשה נמקים נמקים bo na'aseh nemakim nemakim will
be like, where the flesh will rot. ותחת חגורה נקפה v'tachat chagorah
nikpah and explain,
instead of the belt will be נקפה, nikpah, which commonly means like
a rope, but here it says מקום שהיו חגורות בצלצול makom shehayu
chagurot b'tziltzul where they used to gird themselves with a fancy belt,
so also like in the genital area seems to be referred by
the גמרא, נעשה נקפים נקפים na'aseh nekafim nekafim will be made into
wounds. ותחת מעשה מקשה קרחה v'tachat ma'aseh miksheh karchah
and as opposed to a fancy hairdo, baldness. So the way they
read it, מקום שהיו מתקשטות בו, makom shehayu mitkashtot bo, the place
where they would sort of beautify themselves, נעשה קרחים קרחים na'aseh krachim
krachim will be made with bald spots. ותחת פתיגיל מחגורת שק v'tachat
ptigil machagoret sak
as opposed to joy will be girding of sackcloth. Instead of the
sash, okay.
פתחים, petachim, so the way the גמרא is reading it is פתחים,
petachim, the פתח, petach, פתיגיל, ptigil, the openings, which means the genitals,
המביאים לידי גילה hamevi'im lidey gila
which lead to rejoicing, whatever, pleasure, יהיו למחגורת שק yihyu l'machagoret sak
instead will be covered with sackcloth. כי תחת יופי ki tachat yofi
and all of, and כי ki is in exchange for beauty, so
כי ki is presumably like ugliness, but let's see what it says.
אמר רבא היינו דאמרי אינשי, amar Rava haynu d'amrei inshi, that's what
people say, חילופא שופרא קיפא, chilufa shufra kifa, in the place, instead
of beauty we have, you know, sickness or ugliness, how do they
translate קיפא? kifa? Sores. Sores, okay. וספח ה' קדקד בנות ציון, v'sipach
Hashem kodkod bnot Tziyon,
God will bang on the heads or whatever of the daughters of
Zion. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, amar Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina, מלמד
שפרחה בהן צרעת, melamed sheparcha bahen tzara'at, it means that leprosy will,
צרעת, tzara'at, will spread over them. כתיב הכא וספח, ktiv hacha v'sipach,
וכתיב התם, v'ktiv hatam, it says by צרעת, tzara'at, לשאת ולספחת, lasait
v'lasapachat,
one of those plagues of leprosy is called ספחת, sapachat, so that's
what it means, וספח, v'sipach, that this צרעת tzara'at will spread on
them. וה' פתהן יערה, v'Hashem pot'hen ye'areh, God will spill out their
pot, presumably their bread, but we read it as פתחן, pitchan, their
openings. סורא אמר רב יהודה, Sura amar Rav Yehuda,
so רב ושמואל, Rav u'Shmuel, חד אמר שנשפכו כקיתון, chad amar shenishpechu
k'kiton, one says that they will spill out like a, like, you
know, like a pitcher, meaning that their, you know, they'll bleed, you
know, menstrual bleeding or whatever, so it will be an illness, they'll
bleed, you know, profusely. וחד אמר שנעשו פתחיהן כיער, v'chad amar shena'asu
pitechaihen k'yaar,
the place again of their openings, meaning again the genital area, will
be like a יער, yaar, not יערה ye'areh to spill out, but
a יער, yaar, a forest, which means it will be very hairy.
The גמרא actually assumes other גמרות Gemarot that the norm was for
women to shave their genital areas and that that was not considered
to be, that was considered to be, you know, not attractive. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב אנשי ירושלים אנשי שחץ היו. amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav anshei Yerushalayim anshei shachatz hayu.
I know what, we will end with this, so we will get
to this nice.
We go to the משנה or the...?
All right, fine, we'll do two more minutes. People of ירושלים Yerushalayim
were, the men, since we were talking so much about the women
right now, let's not forget the men. The men were actually boastful
and arrogant and also like disgusting. שהיה אדם אומר לחבירו, shehaya adam
omer l'chavero, man said to his friend, במה סעדת היום, bameh sa'adta
hayom, what, what did you eat today? בפת עמילה או בפת שאינה
עמילה, b'pat amila o b'pat she'eina amila, was it a worked loaf
of bread where you worked the dough or not? All of this
was allusions to sexual
activity. Meaning like a virgin or a non-virgin. ביין גודרני או ביין
חרדלי, b'yayin gudrani o b'yayin chardali,
white wine or black wine, talking about the women they slept
with. במטה רחבה או במטה קצרה, b'mita rechava o b'mita katzara,
was it a wide couch you slept on or a narrow couch?
וחבר טוב או בחבר רע, v'chaver tov o v'chaver ra, good friend
or bad friend. אמר רב חסדא וכולן לזנות, amar Rav Chisda v'chulan
liznut, all of these are allusions for sexual sin. Is there a
פסוק? pasuk? No. אמר רב חבא אמר רב יהודה עצי ירושלים, amar
Rav Chaba amar Rav Yehuda atzei Yerushalayim, let's end on a positive
note and also tying into the aromatic perfume, the wood of ירושלים
Yerushalayim של קינמון היו, shel kinamon hayu, was of cinnamon. There used
to be cinnamon growing in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ובשעה שהיו מסיקין מהן, uv'sha'ah
shehayu masikin mehen, and it was so plentiful they would use it
as firewood.
And when they would use it to light a fire, ריחן נודף
בכל ארץ ישראל, reichan nodef b'chol eretz Yisrael, the smell would spread
throughout all of Israel, this beautiful smell. ומשחרבה ירושלים, u'mishecharva Yerushalayim,
and when ירושלים Yerushalayim was destroyed, נגנזו, nignazu, it was hidden. ולא
נשתייר אלא כשעורה, v'lo nishtayer ela k'se'ora, only a tiny bit like
a barley seed it remains, ומשתכח בגיזא דצינצמאי מלכתא, u'mishtachach b'gizei d'Tzintzmai
malkata, and you can find it in the treasure houses of the
queen צינצמאי, Tzintzmai, whoever she is. To be continued tomorrow.